ILGWU. Joint Board shop lists 5780/164
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
The historic revival of the New York dress organization in 1933 created the largest single body of workers within the union. By the 1940s, the Dress Joint Board was composed of Locals 89 (Italian Dressmakers), 22, 60 (Dress Pressers) and the Dress Division of Cutters' Local 10. Added to that, in 1939 the Dress Joint Board took over responsibility for and control over the working conditions and agreements of silk dress production in the Eastern and the Cotton Dress Departments. The Joint Board worked to create a WPA sewing project for unemployed dressmakers, as well as establishing in 1938 a Samplemakers' Labor Bureau. Unfortunately, the lack of styles during the war years caused economic problems, with shrinking production and unemployment. With the collective agreement of March 1944, an industry-wide health and vacation fund covered members of Locals 89, 22 and 60 and included sick benefits, hospitalization, medical services at the Union Health Center, eye exams, and tuberculosis aid, as well as one week's paid vacation. Additionally, a retirement system supplemented the health and vacation fund, the Retirement Fund and Health and Welfare Fund of the Dress Joint Board. Soon, the dress industry was back to pre-war production levels with an increase in styles, though the industry often had difficulty adapting to the postwar retail market and new consumer attitude. The Joint Board launched a large scale organization drive at the end of the decade which was met with resistance, often violent, by "for hire" thugs interfering on picket lines and threatening Joint Board officers. Zimmerman, now a vice-president as well as manager of Local 22, supervised the drive to organize the open shops. It was during this drive that dress presser and temporary organizer William Lurye was murdered in May 1949 as the open shops employed racketeering to prevent unionization. The anti-open shop campaign succeeded in bringing union conditions and standards to the new shops.
The New York Dress Institute was formed with the assistance of the Joint Board in 1941 to promote American fashions and establish New York as the fashion capital. While the Joint Board suspended payments in 1944, the Institute still operated, having fashion shows, distributing fashion photographs for publications, and maintaining the best dressed women list. By 1953, the Dress Institute cut operation due to lack of funds and began operating as the Couture Group of the Dress Institute. At a GEB meeting in 1953, shipping clerks in the dress industry were unionized to form Local 60A, a branch of Local 60. The locals in Joint Board now included Locals 89, 22, and 60-60A Dress Pressers and Shipping Clerks. Julius Hochman resigned as manager of the Dress Joint Board in June 1958 after 29 years (since 1929) to direct the new ILGWU Union Label Department. He was succeeded by Charles Zimmerman, who had been manager of Local 22 for 25 years. 1958 also saw the formation of the Dressmakers' Joint Council, which consisted of the Joint Board, as well as the dress sections of the Eastern Out-of-Town and Northeast Departments. Zimmerman was also manager of the new Joint Council. Sol Greene, assistant director of the Northeast Department, became the new assistant general manager of the Joint Board. The Joint Board in January 1959 was the first ILGWU affiliate to introduce the new union label.
A March 1958 walkout of 105,000 dressmakers in the New York metropolitan area was the first general strike in 25 years. Negotiations with employers began at the end of 1957 and with no resolution in sight, the contracts, set to expire January 1958, were extended for another month. Again, with no agreement in sight, the strike committee set the date of March 5 for the walkout. At ten o'clock that morning, thousands and thousands of garment workers left the shops and made their way into the streets. Soon Madison Square Garden was filled and tens of thousands pickets organized. A few days later, Mayor Wagner called strike leaders and appointed from Senator Lehman and Impartial Chairman Harry Uviller to mediate the strike. The five day general strike resulted in a new contract for workers including wage increases, a 7 hour day/ 35 hour week for piece and time workers with overtime pay, and the establishment of a severance fund.
The decades of the 1960s and 70s saw a decline in shops and jobs in New York City with firms going out of business. In June 1969, Local 38 Theatrical Costume, Ladies Tailors voted to affiliate with the Joint Board, representing theatrical costume workers and custom tailors in departments stores. Additional diversifying included a newly formed Local 159 of office employees in the dress industry. Charles Zimmerman retired on July 1, 1972 as union vice president and manager of the Dress Joint Council and New York Dress Joint Board. Murray Gross, who had been associate general manager since 1969 became the general manager of the Joint Board and Joint Council. The Joint Board now consisted of Locals 89, 22, 60-60A and 159 along with the new Local 38 and 159. March 1974 saw the initial movement to reorganize the Joint Board by combining and merging various departments. By 1975, the New York Dress Joint Board completed restructuring of affiliate locals, and Locals 60-60A, 159, and 38 were merged into existing Locals 22 and 89. Local 22 gained jurisdiction over all dressmakers in Manhattan and Local 89 was designated the local for all Bronx and Brooklyn members. Vice president and general manager Murray Gross retired and Sam Nemaizer became manager after the 1974 convention. There were changes in leadership also as Locals 22 and 89 saw long serving managers began to retire.
In November 1977, the executive committee of the ILGWU General Executive Board enacted a resolution that merged the existing cloak, dress, rainwear and other affiliates in New York, thus ending the separate existence of the New York Cloak and Dress Joint Boards. The New York Cloak-Dress Joint Board and Affiliates consisted of Local 1-35 United Coat, Suit, Rainwear and Allied Workers Union of Manhattan; Local 10 Cutters; Local 22 Dressmakers Union of Manhattan; Local 48 Coat, Suit, Dress, Rainwear and Allied Workers Union of North Brooklyn; Local 77 Coat, Suit, Dress, Rainwear and Allied Workers Union of Queens; Local 89 Coat, Suit, Dress, Rainwear and Allied Workers Union of South Brooklyn; and Local 189 Coat, Suit, Dress, Rainwear and Allied Workers Union of the Bronx. At the same time, sportswear locals previously under the Dress or Cloak Joint Board were now a part of the new New York Sportswear and Allied Workers Joint Board (Local 10 Cutters; Local 23-25 Blouse, Skirt and Sportswear Workers; Local 91 Children's Dressmakers; Local 105 Snowsuit, Infants, and Novelty Sportswear; and Local 155 Knitgoods Workers). The new resolution redrew existing locals' jurisdiction to represent workers along geographic as well as industrial lines. The changes created a more efficient and economical representation of the workers and provided greater organizing ability and bargaining power. E. Howard Molisani, an ILGWU vice-president and manager of the Cloak Joint Board, was elected to serve as the general manager of the new organization. Following his retirement in July 1978, Samuel Nemaizer (formerly manager of the Dress Joint Board) was appointed to succeed Molisani as general manager.
In late 1981, the Joint Board approved a measure to dissolve Locals 48, 77 and 189 to create a stronger financial foundation for the organization. Members were transferred to Locals 22, 1-35 and 89. Local 89 was renamed Local 89-48 to honor the historic significance of the Italian cloakmakers. An October 1984 meeting resulted in more restructuring of the board and locals into a new Local 89-22-1. Changes in the garment industry necessitated the dissolution of the Joint Board and Locals 22 and 89-48. The charter of Local 1-35 was amended to create the new Local 89-22-1. With the consolidation of staff and retirements of managers Samuel Nemaizer, Manuel Gonzalez and Frank Longo, Samuel Byer, associate general manager of the New York Coat-Dress-Rainwear Joint Board was elected manager of Local 89-22-1. The New York Sportswear Joint Board was renamed the New York Joint Board in August 1985, and Locals 62-32 and 66-40 joined the existing affiliates Locals 23-25, 155, 91-105 and 10 and managed by Edgar Romney. After the retirement in 1993 of Samuel Byer, Barbara Laufman was elected manager of Local 89-22-1. Local 89-22-1 was the successor to some of the oldest locals in the union from the coat, dress, suite and rainwear industries, as well as both the New York Dress and Cloak Joint Boards. In July 1922, the New York State District merged with Local 89-22-1.
Scope and Contents
The collection is mainly composed of shop lists. These exist for the Joint Board of Cloak, Skirt, Dress and Reefer Makers' Union, the Joint Board of the Dress and Waistmakers' Union, and the Joint Board of Cloakmakers' Union. There are alphabetized lists of union shops with addresses that also illustrate changes, additions, and deletions to the shops working within the Joint Boards. Also included is a listing of "Manufacturers and Jobbers, Dress Industry," produced by the Research Department in 1940 with information not only contained to New York City, but to locations across the United States.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records 5780/041: ILGWU. New York Cloak Joint Board payroll analysis 5780/020: ILGWU. New York Cloak Joint Board records 5780/032: ILGWU. New York Cloak Joint Board minutes 5780/033: ILGWU. New York Dress Joint Board minutes
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives 227 Ives Hall Tower Road Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheelref@cornell.edu https://catherwood.library.cornell.edu/kheel/
Compiled by:
C. Berne, July 27, 2009
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, February 28, 2014
Women's clothing industry -- United States; Women's clothing industry -- New York (State); Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Labor unions -- Clothing workers -- New York (State); Clothing workers -- United States; Clothing workers -- New York (State); Industrial relations -- United States; Industrial relations -- New York (State); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. New York Cloak Joint Board
5521552
- Union Shops in Contractual Relations with the Joint Board, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Cloak, Skirt, Dress, and Reefer Makers' Union. August 24
- ILGWU Joint Board, Dress and Waistmakers Union. Shop List, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  New York City
- ILGWU Joint Board Cloak, Suit, Skirt, and Reefer Makers' Unions. Union Shops - Changes, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- ILGWU Joint Board Cloak, Suit, Skirt, and Reefer Makers' Unions. Union Shops, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Volume 2
- ILGWU Joint Board Cloak, Suit, Skirt, and Reefer Makers' Unions. Union Shops., 1943 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Volume 1
- ILGWU Joint Board Cloak, Suit, Skirt, and Reefer Makers' Unions. Union Shops, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- ILGWU Joint Board Cloak, Suit, Skirt, and Reefer Makers' Unions. Union Shops, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- ILGWU Joint Board Dress and Waistmakers' Union. Changes in Union Shop Lists, 1942-1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- ILGWU Joint Board Cloak, Suit, Skirt, and Reefer Makers' Union. Union Shops, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- ILGWU Joint Board Cloak, Suit, Skirt, and Reefer Makers' Union. Union Shops, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- ILGWU Joint Board Dress and Waistmakers' Union. Shop List, 1936-1940 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- ILGWU Joint Board Dress and Waistmakers Union. Shop List, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- ILGWU Joint Board Cloakmakers' Union. Union Shops, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- ILGWU Research Department. Manufactures and Jobbers, Dress Industry, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  September
- ILGWU Joint Board, Dress and Waistmakers' Union, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  January 9